Guide to the Samuel Simon Leibowitz papers, 1939-1976.
Leibowitz, Samuel Simon papers, 1939-1976.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Samuel Simon Leibowitz papers, 1939-1976.
3923
Samuel Simon Leibowitz, 1893-1978.
4 cubic ft.
Correspondence, notes, manuscripts, newspaper clippings, articles, legal documents, photographs, and audiotapes.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes papers relating to the career and interests of Samuel Simon Leibowitz, who earned his B.A. and his LL.B. from Cornell University. As a lawyer, he defended, and ultimately exonerated, the Scottsboro Boys. He later became a judge on the New York Supreme Court, where he remained until mandatory retirement at age 76.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Samuel Simon Leibowitz earned his B.A. and his LL.B. from Cornell University. As a lawyer, he defended, and ultimately exonerated, the Scottsboro Boys. He later became a judge on the New York Supreme Court, where he remained until mandatory retirement at age 76.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes correspondence, notes and manuscripts for speeches, testimonials and debates, reports, newspaper clippings and articles, legal documents, photographs, and tapes pertaining to subjects and criminal cases of interest to Leibowitz, including capital punishment, prison reform, narcotics, and juvenile delinquency.
Also, tape recording and transcript of an interview with Samuel Leibowitz discussing his background, his education at Cornell, and his career as a lawyer and judge, ca. 1971 (the interviewer is only referred to as John).
Also, a transcript of an interview Leibowitz gave in 1971 to WVBR Radio broadcast ("Newsbeat"), in which he discusses prisoner rehabilitation, Manson trial, Scottsboro case, police brutality and civilian review boards, police corruption, victimless crimes (drugs), Cornell Law School, political activism, Al Capone, first degree punishment, Sacco and Vanzetti case, Governor Rockefeller, political cases, young attorneys, and Einstein; the transcript is numbered "tr.489-490".
SUBJECTS
Names:
Samuel Simon Leibowitz, 1893-1978.; Capone, Al, 1899-1947; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955
Subjects:
Scottsboro Trial, Scottsboro, Ala., 1931; Sacco-Vanzetti Trial, Dedham, Mass., 1921; Capital punishment.; Drug abuse.; Juvenile delinquency.; Narcotics.; Prison reformers.; Criminals.; Crime.; Lawyers.; Judges.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
CONTAINER LIST
- Capital punishment
  - Great Britain Royal Commission on Capital Punishment, 1949-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Capital punishment statistics, ca. 1950-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Religion; Black and Poor; Deterent - notes and articles, ca. 1956-1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - D.A. Association Forum on Capital Punishment, Jan. 27, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Symposium at D.A. Association; SSL and D.A. Maskell TV debate; SSL reply to CBS editorial; Judge's poll; SSL - Sellin debate; SSL minutes - Stokes and Garner cases; Ch. 5 discussion - Lyons and Brown, Mar. 18, 1973, 1961-1973 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Open Mind, NBC-TV - A Debate on Capital Punishment, Feb. 18, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence re: Open Mind, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Public hearing on capital punishment, Dec. 7, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Testimonial and speech notes - New York Assembly, Oct. 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - NYS Legislative Committee on Revision of Penal Law, Dec. 7, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Court of Common Please, Delaware Co., May 2, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Coram Nobis hearing: The People of NYS vs. Raymond Gardner, Sept. 23, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Taxi drivers; Taxi News, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Proposed death penalty bill, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Public hearing - CBS-TV, July 9, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Notes, addresses
    - Assembly hearing, Oct. 16, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - GABE Ch. 5, Mar. 18, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Young lawyers, Mar. 30, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, ca. 1961-1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Pro and con press, ca. 1960-1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photographs: Hitler, Hauptmann, Lepke, Snyder, and Gray (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Juvenile delinquency
  - Notes for speeches, ca. 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, notes, clippings, 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Talk, NY Young Republic Club, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Peoria Bar Association, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Notes and clippings, ca. 1953-1958 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Clippings, ca. 1960-1974 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Murtagh, John M. (Judge) People of NYS vs.
  - Legal documents, Kings Co., NY, stenographers minutes, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, legal documents (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Narcotics
  - Major articles, ca. 1963-1967 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Hearings before the Select Committee on Crime, House of Representatives, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Clippings: law enforcement, police - D.A.'s; courts, ca. 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Narcotics - correspondence or copies of letters: Ed. Benes, Mitchell; Paul L. Perito; Ambassador Arthur K. Watson; William J. Durkin; John E. Ingersoll; Congressman Vanick; Sen. Murphy; Gov. Rockefeller; Sen. Edward M. Kennedy; Marseille - Cusser interview; Blount urges boycott before Congressional committee, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Press clips re: Rockefeller tough laws (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Articles (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Before legislative commission (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newsday series: "The Heroin Trail", 1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Clippings and articles, ca. 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Speech material, various topics; Congressional hearing; drug abuse in suburbia, ca. 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Scaglia, Francois, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Prisons
  - Prisons - articles: conditions and proposed reforms; parole (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Addresses: Middle Atlantic states, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Clippings (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1939-1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Prisons (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Speech, Mar. 19, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Testimony (Dunne), Mar. 21, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Sen. Dunne report, Oct. 5, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - News clips (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Prison newsclips, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Prison newsclips, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Meany (correspondence with), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Age of Machinery (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Census and miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Leniency (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Prison riots, 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Attica, articles: Time ("A Model Prison"), Newsweek, U.S. News (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Auburn: Becker (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Prison and reform, sentencing, 1972-1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Notes correspondence, articles, 1949-1958 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, notes, articles, speeches, 1952-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous
  - Transcript of an interview Leibowitz gave in 1971 to WVBR Radio broadcast ("Newsbeat"), tr.489-490
  - Not classified: press clips, illiteracy, schools, Miami, Columbia Law School, Mad Bomber, ca. 1941-1972 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Tapes: 97 tapes covering the following subjects: (Box 3-4)
    Abortion
    Capital punishment
    Drugs
    Juvenile delinquency
    Prisons
    Trial technique
    Violence in schools
    Miscellaneous: radio and television talks